Here we
[Music]
go. Hey guys, I'm Manar Muhawish.
Earlier this month on Behind the
Headline, I spoke with CIA whistleblower
John Kuryaku, who explained how oil and
resources have been the driving force
behind every US military operation in
the Middle East since the 1970s. From
Iraq, Iran, and Afghanistan to where we
are today in Syria. Kuryaku noted that
these conflicts can be traced back to an
alliance cemented between President
Franklin D. Roosevelt and the House of
Sah in 1943, roughly 10 years after
Standard Oil of California, which later
became Chevron discovered the world's
second largest oil reserves in Saudi
Arabia. Now, in return for giving the
United States control of their oil
reserves and airspace, Saudi Arabia
would gain control over the oil market
and enjoy the power, money, and
influence that comes with it. But Saudi
Arabia has used this very power, money,
and influence to divide and conquer the
Middle East and many parts of Africa
through the unleashing of terrorism. Of
course, none of that would be possible
without the financial and arms support
from its Western allies, including the
United States. Pentagon officials have
told me that Saudi Arabia has a printing
press operation worth billions that is
responsible for not just counterfeiting
hadith or traditions and sayings of the
prophet Muhammad but even manufacturing
Islamic history books to be exported
throughout the Muslim world. Now, the
effects of these efforts to rewrite the
history of a faith of over 1.5 billion
people to suit the Saudi political
agenda that limit women's rights,
promote radicalism and tyrannical
leadership are rippling across the
region and the world through radical
groups like ISIS and al-Nusra front.
These are the very same terror groups
the United States claims to be fighting
in its so-called war on terror. to make
sense of this often unhealthy and
confusing relationship of
interdependency and conflicting agendas
is CIA whistleblower John Keryaku again.
Take a
look. So, thank you so much, John, for
joining me again. Um, you know,
continuing our conversation from earlier
this month in 1943, uh, President
Roosevelt declared, "The defense of
Saudi Arabia is vital to the defense of
the United States." In a nutshell, um,
what has this meant for US foreign
policy in the Middle East? Oh, I think
this has been the the keystone of
American foreign policy in the Middle
East, for better or for worse. I mean,
it's always great to have friends in the
region, especially when you find
yourself in a time of war and you
suddenly need to have air bases or naval
bases. But at the same time, we've
committed ourselves uh now for for well
more than half a century to uh defending
um really a a right-wing an extreme
right-wing uh government that has no
respect for human rights, no respect for
women's rights, no respect for religious
freedoms, and um and in exchange we we
buy their oil. We we really have a very
uh simple relationship with the Saudis.
we buy their oil and they buy our uh
military hardware. It it's really that
simple. Otherwise, we generally agree on
very little in terms of of policy. But
with that said, we are committed to the
survival of the also regime and um we
have proven time and again that we will
walk away from our own commitments to
international law and to human rights in
order to defend and protect that regime.
And you know, I've actually interviewed,
and I told you this before, former
Pentagon officials um like Wayne,
Colonel Wayne Quist, who have said
blatantly that Saudi Arabia is the
largest manufacturer of radicalism in
the world. In fact, Saudi Arabia
literally engineers um and publishes
thousands of fake hadiths and books and
historical books about Islam and its
history to justify their tyrannical rule
while pushing an extremist perverted um
radical ideology uh and perspective of
you know Sunni Islam. Of course, most
Sunnis would not appreciate that if they
if they only knew. um their efforts are
making their way across Sunni mosques
and schools and madrasas in in the
Middle East and Africa and have created
groups like monster groups like ISIS and
al-Nusra. So my question for you is I
mean what else do we need to know about
Saudi Arabia's terror factory?
Oh, I have always believed that Saudi
Arabia was the was the primary uh
generator and creator of radicals and
radical movements around not just the
region but around the world. The it's
it's the entire it's not just the
government uh that that does this and
that supports this extre extremism. It's
the entire um structure of government
and society in Saudi Arabia. You know,
when you have when you have a chairman
of the like um well, the former
chairman, Sheikh bin Baz, for
example, who swore until the day he died
that the earth was flat and anyone who
argued that the earth was round was
subject to the death penalty. Uh we have
a we the Saudis have a new uh uh leader
in the Ulam by the name of Kakani who's
from a very honorable and very old
family but he has done absolutely
nothing to improve as I said human
rights uh political
discourse the rights of women anything
like that in Saudi Arabia. So really,
you have you have a group of of
religious
extremists who tell the government and
its leaders what they should think and
what they should do. Now, behind closed
doors, they think and do whatever they
want. We know that that uh most if not
all of the senior royals, for example,
drink alcohol. Um they consort with
women. They do all the things that the
average Saudi is not allowed to do or
not supposed to do. But in Saudi Arabia,
everybody else is expected to tow the
line. So that's domestically.
Internationally, you have a government
in Riyad that supports movements around
the region and around the world that the
United States and specifically the State
Department have identified as terrorist
groups. I'm talking about the Nusra
front, for example. I'm talking about
even even earlier uh the some of the
jihadi groups in Afghanistan in the
1980s and
1990s. I'm talking about the Hambali
movement for example in Southeast Asia.
So here we find ourselves as an American
government fighting these groups around
the world when in fact our dear friends
the Saudis are organizing them and
financing them and they think nothing of
of just flouting that to us. And of
course, I mean, as you mentioned, this
is politically motivated, not actually
motivated, since a lot of these hadith
that they're actually using are
manufactured and rewritten by
themselves. Um, but speaking of this
push for terrorism, uh, let's talk about
the the Shia oil crescent. Most people
don't know that the Shia in the Middle
East actually reside along uh the major
oil and gas fields across the Middle
East. And that just so happens to be
where um, US bases are ba are based. and
then also where Saudi influence is the
highest. Um so how can so how can you
know understanding this Shia oil base um
how can this help us understand the
economic implications of Saudi Arabia's
anti-SI propaganda
um and also it's its anti- um moderate
Sunni propaganda as well and how has our
war on terror only enabled Saudi
Arabia's religious cleansing of the
Middle East? Oh, that is that is such an
important question and it's it's
something that that I wish everybody who
who watched the Middle East or studied
the Middle East could understand. You're
exactly right that most of the areas all
through the Middle East, specifically um
Iraq, Iran, and Saudi Arabia that have
oil are generally populated by Shia
Muslims.
Now the Saudi government and really
before the the second Gulf War, the
Iraqi government under Saddam Hussein
have done everything possible to make
sure not only that Shia do not control
uh the oil fields or the oil industry,
but even the Shia don't benefit at all
from the money that oil brings in. So
that's why Saudi Arabia, as wealthy a
country as it is, has so many poor
people and most of those poor people are
Shia Muslims. Now you see the same kind
of thing in Bahrain, too. Bahrain is a
majority Shia country. It's ruled by a
Sunni royal family. And instead of
spreading the wealth and trying to um
trying to raise the economic status of
their own Shia Muslims, they've instead
begun importing people from Syria and
and Pakistan primarily and giving them
Bahraini citizenship so that Sunnis
become the majority in
Bahrain. You see that all over the place
in the region, but the Saudis really are
the most heavy-handed about it. the
Saudis are the ones that use the iron
fist. Um, and the the whole name of the
game really is just control of the oil
and control of the money. So, this use
of, you know, religious extremism, I
mean, obviously the Saudi monarchy and
these Gulf Arab states don't really
represent Sunni Islam. Um, I I I'm sure
that most Sunnis would disagree with
that. Um, and would say that they do not
represent the religion. No, you're
absolutely right. So this is this is not
what Sunni Islam is all about. Not at
all. So how are they able to do this? I
mean we talked a little bit about um the
manufacturing of hadiths and influencing
um these books, but how exactly are they
able to push this ideology and be
successful um in brainwashing people to
follow this route? Well, I think what
most Americans don't understand is that
Saudi Arabia really is a very closed
society. It's It's not as closed as
North Korea certainly, but but you know,
try to get into Saudi Arabia without a
without a sponsor and you can't get into
Saudi Arabia. The Saudis were the were
the last government in the Middle East
to allow broadcast television in their
country, for example. And the only
reason they finally allowed television
is because Shikbin Baz was convinced or
became convinced that at least if they
had television, they could broadcast the
Quran 24 hours a day. And so at least
when I lived in Saudi Arabia um there
were two Arabic language channels, one
English language channel and it was one
channel was just Quran 20 24 hours a
day. The other was religious discussion
uh religious uh themed programming and
then every once in a while they would
put in a an episode of Doogie Hower or
the Waltons or something like that. It
was very odd. This is a way for the
Saudi government to propagandize their
own people. And over these many, many
years, they've convinced their own
people, or at least many of their own
people, that this brand of of Sunni
Islam, this this Wahhabi brand of Sunni
Islam is the correct path. This is
really the only true Islam. And if you
talk to Saudis today, uh many of them uh
really believe that. Wow. That is just
absolutely insane. I mean the media of
course you know at the end always
becomes the lap dog of those in power
but with all this talk about
manufacturing um terrorism and
instability through the use of Wahhabi
uh Islam you know there's also a real
call for freedom you know amongst Sunnis
even to reject this ideology and Shiites
to reject um this kind of oppression um
but it seems like nearly every
revolution across the Middle East um has
been hijacked by Saudi Arabia's
political ambitions Um, in Egypt is a
really good example. Not that the Muslim
Brotherhood was any better, but you
know, the, you know, the CC government,
you know, o overthrew the Muslim
Brotherhood government. And now, you
know, Egypt is the largest recipient of
funds and arms um from Saudi Arabia. And
in Syria, we have terror groups funded
and armed by Saudi Arabia, ISIS and
al-Nusra flourishing. And in Bahin, you
talked a little bit about um the uh the
demographic engineering. So, what do
regular people in the Middle East need
to do to truly free themselves from both
Western imperialism, because let's be
honest here, this is, you know, this is
able to happen because of Western
imperialism and interests, um, and also
Saudi Arabia's political ambitions. What
do people really need to do to free
themselves from this? There's there's
really no easy answer to that question.
That that's a very important and really
a very difficult question. I I would say
that if there is going to be any change,
any real change in the Middle East, it's
going to take decades and it's going to
have to be
revolutionary, but not revolutionary in
a violent way. Revolutionary in a
democratic way. We we saw we saw really
the beginnings of a of a truly
democratic um uprising at the very start
of the Arab Spring in Tunisia. And I
think that for there to be any success
in other countries, they're going to
have to to follow that Tunisian model,
at least from the early days of of the
uprising. Now, honestly, I don't think
there's there ever going to be any kind
of real change, revolutionary change in
Saudi Arabia. And you're right about the
Saudis um really really not just
supporting the CC government, but
bankrolling the CC government and
ensuring its its survival. Saudi Arabia
has a very long history of meddling in
Egyptian internal affairs going back to
1958 and to the to the revolution the
nationalist revolution in in Egypt in
1958.
So anybody participating in a popular
uprising is going to have to to fight
against Saudi money and Saudi weapons.
And honestly, I I wish I could say that
that there's a model, a real model uh
for transition to democracy in the
Middle East that doesn't include blood
spilled in the streets, but I think such
a model doesn't really exist. The only
way you're going to be able to to
counter the effects of Saudi involvement
in other regional countries is is by
shedding blood. Wow. That's very
unfortunate. I mean, of course, I have a
slightly terrible Yeah. And I and I and
I you know I understand what you're
saying but I think you know the bigger
picture is that we're seeing a divide
and conquer taking place from Egypt to
Syria to Iraq to Yemen and this push
from uh you know religious u you know
sectarianism as as you put it. So I
really think you know we have to hope
for some unity amongst the people.
Absolutely right. Absolutely right. And
and there is there there is one model I
would say it's not a perfect model but
there there is one country that at least
has begun a transition into into a
uniquely Middle Eastern form of
semi-democracy and and I think that's
Kuwait. You know, Kuwaitis used to march
in at the streets in the 1980s, nearly
1990s, and and there were riots and the
police would fire tear gas and rubber
bullets, and they would arrest a dozen
or two dozen people and then let them
out of prison a couple of weeks or a
couple of months later. Um, but this
continued to go on after the Iraqi
invasion and occupation, after the
reestablishment of the monarchy in
Kuwait, people still took to the streets
and the Savah family finally agreed that
there had to be democratic elections.
Now, the elections were stacked in a way
in that the constitution was rewritten
so that tribal families got an
inordinately large number of
parliamentary seats. But at the same
time over the years even those tribal
families have have really turned in
favor of democracy. So while you still
have a monarchy it's much more of a
constitutional monarchy now than it was
20 or 30 years ago and you really do
have a form of democracy in Kuwait
that's unique to the Middle East. I
think that's really the model and
actually in Kuwait they do I mean
absolutely represent uh more of that
unity because they do have the Sunni
large Sunni large Shia population and
they're living side by side peacefully
right engaging in very good relations.
So hopefully that can be a model for the
rest of the Middle East. Um I could and
may I add something to that too?
Absolutely. Go ahead. Kuwait had a
Kuwait had a a tough time uh with their
with elements of their Shia community in
the early 1980s. There was a Hezbollah
pres presence in Kuwait in the early
1980s and the Kuwaiti royal family
really reacted with a very heavy hand
and they went in and literally flattened
with bulldozers an entire Shia
neighborhood where this Hispa cell uh
had established itself. They killed
people. They arrested a lot of people
and then they immediately began to try
to rebuild relations, sectarian
relations in the country. Again, one of
the one of the reasons why that was sort
of propelled was because of the Iraqi
invasion of Kuwait. But now, you know,
you've got a country that's 40 or 45%
Shia. It has a Sunni royal family, but
Shia are heavily represented in the uh
in the uh majus and Shia have important
positions of authority. There are Shia
cabinet ministers. Many of the prominent
business families, the Bahanis, for
example, are Shia Muslims and people
seem to get along well in uh in Kuwait.
Again, I I think that might be a model
for the rest of the region. So, what are
they doing that's so different? I mean,
they're represented, but what exactly is
happening um at the base? At the base,
they've given Shia Muslims exactly the
same rights that Sunnis have. Plain and
simple. That easy. It's easy. Awesome.
Well, thank you so much, John. It's a
pleasure to talk to you again and
hopefully we'll have you on again
hopefully in another couple weeks and we
can continue the conversation about US
relations in the Middle. Appreciate it.
Thanks very much for having me. Thank
you.